<sourceDoc xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="Frankenstein">
		<surface facs="#f000">
			<line>satisfied that nothing on earth will have the power</line>
			<line>to interrupt my tranquillity.</line>
			<line>“Do not let this letter disturb you; do not</line>
			<line>answer tomorrow, or the next day, or even until</line>
			<line>you come, if it will give you pain. My uncle will</line>
			<line>send me news of your health, and if I see but</line>
			<line>one smile on your lips when we meet, occasioned</line>
			<line>by this or any other exertion of mine, I</line>
			<line>shall need no other happiness.</line>
			<line/>
			<line>Elizabeth Lavenza</line>
			<line/>
			<line>Geneva, May 18th, 17—</line>
			<line/>
			<line>This letter revived in my memory what I had</line>
			<line>before forgotten, the threat of the fiend—“I will be</line>
			<line>with you on your wedding-night!” Such was my</line>
		</surface>
		<surface facs="#f001">
			<line>sentence, and on that night would the dæmon employ</line>
			<line>every art to destroy me and tear me from the</line>
			<line>glimpse of happiness which promised partly to console</line>
			<line>my sufferings. On that night he had determined</line>
			<line>to consummate his crimes by my death. Well, be it so;</line>
			<line>a deadly struggle would then assuredly take place,</line>
			<line>in which if he were victorious I should be at</line>
			<line>peace and his power over me be at an end. If</line>
			<line>he were vanquished, I should be a free man. Alas!</line>
			<line>What freedom? Such as the peasant enjoys when</line>
			<line>his family have been massacred before his</line>
			<line>eyes, his cottage burnt, his lands laid waste, and he is</line>
			<line>turned adrift, homeless, penniless, and alone, but</line>
			<line>free. Such would be my liberty except that in</line>
			<line>my Elizabeth I possessed a treasure, alas,</line>
			<line>balanced by those horrors of remorse and guilt</line>
			<line>which would pursue me until death.</line>
			<line>Sweet and beloved Elizabeth! I read and re-</line>
			<line>read her letter, and some softened feelings stole</line>
		</surface>
	</sourceDoc>